Can I Find My Mind by Practicing Dhyana?
Not that I have an issue,
I am just curious.
What is dhyana?
Is it same as meditation?
I heard that the mind is Buddha.
Can I find my mind if I practice dhyana?
That doesn't really make sense.
If I practice dhyana or meditate,
can I find my mind?
What should I do to find mind?
Do you not have a mind?
I do. But I don't know
if my thoughts are the same as my mind.
I heard we need to overcome our minds,
so I want to find this "mind".
Our mind is always working.
Why would you want to make
such an effort to find it?
It aries naturally and constantly
even when you do not look for it.
How do I practice dhyana?
Why do you want to practice dhyana?
Is it only for monks?
Well, why do you want to practice dhyana?
To find my mind.
Why do you want to find your mind?
I think it might help me
to control my thoughts.
Then just control your thoughts.
So, is it the mind
that control the thoughts?
What kind of thoughts you want to control?
(Questioner) Random thoughts..
(Sunim) Random thoughts?
(Questioner) Negative thoughts.
(Sunim) Negative thoughts?
We are structured psycologically
to have negative thoughts naturally.
When those thoughts arise,
just leave it as it is.
Monks practice dhyana.
Ordinary people can't do it?
Sure you can.
I want to know how to do it.
Ok but I am asking why you want to know.
Well..why do I want to know?
Just to clear my mind.
(Audience Laughter)
That is such a vauge thought..
Stay there. We are not done yet.
(Sunim) There are some people who ruin
their lives and their family
because of religion
as there are such absurd people
like this person in this world.
Wake up. You might think that you are
sophisticated if you ask a question like,
"How do I practice dhyana?"
But it is not sophisticated at all.
It is not sophisticated.
If you find a word that you don't
understand while you are reading at home..
You can just search on your computer
or look it up in a dictionary.
Why fuss over it?
There are many words
that even Buddhists wouldn't understand
unless you go to a temple to ask.
Don't you know how to search
for those words online
in case you don't know the meaning of it?
(Audience Laughter)
I search as well. But I find Buddhism
a bit difficult for regular person
to understand or accept as a religion
just by reading about it.
Then what are you going to do
with such a difficult Buddhism?
I really don't understand.
(Audience Laughter)
What are you going to do
with this difficult Buddhism?
by practicing Buddhism?
(Questioner) I think I can live a life
only by having certain religion.
Then how can rabbits and squirrles live?
Rabbits live well
and squirrels live well, too.
I am telling you from the beginning
that you are thinking nonsense.
Rabbits live fine without any religion.
Same for squirrels.
You can live without religion in this
world. Half of Koreans are not religious.
Isn't that why so many people
become mentally ill?
Do you think our country will be better
if we all become Christians?
if we all become Buddhist? No.
As long as Koreans have this kind
of mentality,
things would stay the same.
It won't matter whether they are
Christians, Buddhists, or atheists.
It has nothing to do with religion.
Because of your attitude towards religion,
whether you go to church
because you are curious about the God
or go to a temple
because you are curious about dhyana,
there will be no difference.
Because your life remains the same.
There is a reason
why I question you this way.
People ask me, "How should I pray?
How can I practice dhyana?"
Those are quite normal questions, right?
You think I should just tell you
how to pray or how to practice dhyana.
But I ask you back why do you want to pray
or why do you want to practice dhyana.
I ask you because there are too many cases
where you live your lives
by following others.
Just doing what others are doing..
If someone passing by tells you,
"If you don't believe in god,
you will go to hell,"
then you all of sudden get scared
and ask, "Am I really going to hell?"
And listen to these random people,
believe in some random passage
in some book somewhere.
You watch closely what others are doing.
All these just make your life
such a mindless.
Why do you care what others say?
No matter what they say.
If someone says, "You will go
to hell if you don't believe in god"
then just say, "I see. Thank you."
Why should you get scared?
It is not that person's fault..
It is your problem.
You get easily swayed by what others say
because you don't have firm mind.
You pray because others do.
Just like a copy cat.
That's why when someone asks me
how to pray,
I ask back, "Why do you want to pray?"
Then answer goes,
"Because I heard that it is good for you."
So I ask, "You are not good now?"
Then they would respond, "No, I am good."
"Then why do you need to pray?"
"Because I heard that it is good to pray."
"So you are saying that you are not good."
"No, I am fine," they say..
They are just totally out of their mind..
(Audience Laughter)
It is very simple for me
to literally answer your questions.
But the reason for me to keep asking back
is to tell you that you should wake up.
Do not keep following what others do.
Wake up and approach your life
with your own mindset.
"Should practice dhyana
because monks are doing it?"
That is just following and copying others.
Even if the whole world
is practicing dhyana, you don't have to.
Then, what should regular people do
to wake up?
What are you confused about?
Ask me directly
what you are confused about in your life.
What is the biggest problem
you are facing in your life?
You don't have any problem?
(Questioner) No.
No problems at all?
Then why do you want to practice dhyana?
You don't have any problem.
You know how people get agitated..
Now you are talking.
So you get agitated?
(Questioner) I want to control it.
You should have just asked
a simple question.
"I get agitated all the time.
What can I do?"
Yes, you are right.
(Laugher, Applause)
You were beating around the bush,
asking about dhyana.
Everyone gets agitated.
Do we get agitated as there are things
that supposed to cause you agitation?
If you look closely, it is not true.
Being agitated is also a kind of habit.
Your habit.
Do you understand?
How did you acquire this kind of habit?
How did you acquire
a habit of being agitated?
Everyone has a basic belief that they are
right. Every single one has.
This is caused by a limitation on
how people recognize things.
Here is a table, right?
When you look at this table, is it
in front of you or is it behind you?
(Questioner) In front of me.
It is in front of you.
(Questioner) Yes.
Then when I look at this table, is it
in front of me? In the back? On the side?
(Questioner) On the side.
It is on my side.
Where is this table really located at?
Front or side?
(Audience Laughter)
(Questioner) In its place.
What? But we recognize the world
in our own perspective.
That's why, for me, it is on my left side.
But the table is on the left only
because I am looking at it
by putting myself in the center.
Table itself is not on the left.
However, we end up creating misperception.
I take myself away from the equation and
just think that the table is on the left.
You take yourself away from the equation
and just say that it is in the front.
Thus, a conflict arises.
"What? It is on the side.
What do you mean it is in the front?"
After repeating this two or three times
trying to convince the other,
you get agitated.
We get agitated when we are caught up
with a thought that we are right.
We see things from our own perspective
with us in the center.
So we think we are always right.
It is the same
in married couple's relationship.
How is this called in old saying?
Your wife is right in the kitchen and
your mother is right in the living room.
The husband is right
if you listen to what he says,
wife is right if you listen to her.
North is right
if you listen to them in the north,
South is right
if you listen to them in the south.
The right wing and left wing both make
sense when you listen to them each.
Things are all very different
as you can see.
When you go to church,
Christianity seems to make sense.
Buddhism seems to make sense when you go
to temple and hear what they say.
So what is the objective condition?
Everyone is different.
People's thoughts are all different.
This is the only thing that is objective.
There is no right and wrong.
But if you look at things
on your own perspective,
things that are just "different" becomes
"I am 'right' and you are 'wrong.'"
That's why you get agitated.
Do you understand the logic now?
Understanding the logic means
that your head got it.
You understand.
This means that you are able to rationally
understand "Right, that is true."
But the way you have been reacting to
things from your own perspective
for a long time has been repeated,
not just once or twice
but hundreds of thousand times.
And it became a habit of yours.
That's why you will automatically think,
"you are wrong" as something happens.
Your mind reacts right away
before your head can control it.
Your immediate response is
"He is wrong, that is a nonsense."
When you get agitated, you are captured by
self-centered thought of you being right.
But you cannot notice immediately.
Only after you get upset,
you realize that you were mad at others.
Thus, in order for you to not get agitated
or get agitated less,
you have to remind yourself that
there is no such thing as being right.
You already understood this
in your head, right?
Keep reminding yourself on this.
Even if you think this way, you will
automatically react the other way.
If you constantly remind yourself,
your subconsiousness will contradict
itself between "I am right" and
"There is no such thing as me
being right."
Then even if you get agitated,
you will quickly realize,
"Oh, I am getting agitated again,"
and your feeling will subside.
You can get rid of the agitation
by keeping repeating this practice.
It's much easier to fix
a habit of agitation.
if you experience this very deeply
in a retreat
compared to just listening to
my explanation.
You can fix it.
It is not important whether it is
meditation or practicing dhyana.
Prayer? These are not important.
Then what is practicing dhyana really?
I will ask. Try to answer this question.
Who are you? Just casually talk to me.
(Questioner) I am me.
Who is me?
(Questioner) A woman.
Then all the women in this room is you?
(Audience Laughter)
Who are you?
Don't overthink.
Just tell me what comes to your mind.
Whatever thoughts pops up.
(Questioner) Whatever comes to my mind?
Lee Kwang Ae.
Is Lee Kwang Ae you or your name?
(Questioner) My name.
Don't tell me your name.
I did not ask what your name is.
Who are you?
(Questioner) I am me.
Who is "me"?
Right. well, I don't really know who I am.
Is my mind me?
I am not asking about your mind.
I am asking who you are.
(Questioner) A person.
Everyone here is a person.
Is everyone here you?
Who are you?
I read this in a book.
I am a mixture of air, mountain, wind
and environment all put together.
OK. So if I mix air, mountain, wind
and water, then does it become you?
A relationship built based off to
those mixture.
Is it you? Or is it your thought?
(Questioner) My thought.
Who are you?
If you still cannot answer the question,
then you should start finding out
who you are.
We say, I, I, I, I, all the time
in our life. Right?
Who is this "I"?
We have to study this.
Who is this thing we call "I"?
Who is getting angry?
Is it me getting angry? What am I?
What is "I"? Searching for its meaning is
what practicing dhyana is.
So it has nothing to do with
whether you being a monk or not.
It does not matter where you search
for youself, temple or house.
It does not matter whether you do it
while seating down or while standing up.
But the real problem is whether you will
keep searching for youself or not.
If you continue the search,
you will get the answer.
If you don't pursue
even after being a monk,
you will not find an answer
for your question.
It has nothing to do with being a monk.
You can seek it as a Christian,
or as an atheist.
Thank you.
(Audience Applause)